A Guide to the Jefferson-Kirk Manuscripts Relating to Thomas Jefferson and the Jefferson and Randolph Families, 1790-1901
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Jefferson-Kirk Manuscripts Relating to Thomas Jefferson and the Jefferson and Randolph Families 1790-1901
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5291
The collection consists of 41 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was deposited in the Library by Mrs. Page Kirk, 1956 February 8.
Scope and Content
The collection includes an early plan of Monticello; plat of Harrison family lands in Jefferson's hand; letter, 1805 April 5, Jefferson to John Barnes, and letter press copy of letter, 1800 March 4, to Henry Remsen; letter, 1812 September 23, Mrs. Molly Lewis to Jefferson; letter, 1803 October 30, Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Jefferson.
Letter, 1830, November 14, Samuel Smith to Thomas Jefferson Randolph; list of Jefferson's art objects in his hand; plat, in Jefferson's hand, of lands of N.M. Lewis; bank statement with notes in Jefferson's hand; account of a visit to Monticello, 1899, by Emma Frances Allen. Also included are other miscellaneous items including a lottery tickets, a facsimile of a letter to Craven Peyton, two locks of Jefferson's hair, newspaper clippings concerning Jefferson's desk, and other printed matter.
Also receipts from sale held at Monticello, 1827, after Jefferson's death, including slaves, furniture, art, china, and land. Purchasers include relatives and friends Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., Thomas Jefferson Randolph, Cornelia Randolph, Nicholas Philip Trist, Joseph Coolidge, Charles Bankhead, John Wayles Eppes and Edward Coles; University of Virginia professors Charles Bonnycastle and George Blaettermann; and local residents and business associates Craven Peyton, John M. Perry, Peachey R. Gilmer, Charles Everett, and Martin Dawson.
Contents List
- Thomas Jefferson Early Drawing Of Monticello, [1771-1772], AD, 1 p.; Photostat; Original. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Study for final elevation of the first version. #9828; See Nichols, N-47.
- John Grant, Jeweler of London, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Purchased coffee urn.
- Lacey, Jeweler of London, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Purchased tea tray.
- William Leigh, Jeweler of London, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Purchased stewing dish and top.
- Alexander Mackintosh, Sadler of London, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:5)
  Purchased bit.
- E. Pugh, Jeweler of London and to Princess Amelia, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:6)
  Purchased small silver cross.
- Mr. Price, Jeweler of London, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Purchased silver candlestick.
- Thomas Roe, Linen Draper of the Strand, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Purchased calico.
- James Shrapnell, Goldsmith of Charing Cross, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:9)
  Purchased butter boats, pudding dish.
- William Sutton, Jeweler of London, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Purchased coffee jar.
- J. Thomas, Jeweler of London, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Purchased sword chains.
- Samuel Wildman, Jeweler of London, Business Card, [1786], D, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:12)
  Purchased silver cross.
- Five cards of English and French craftsmen and shopkeepers, [ca. 1790], D, 6 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 1:13)
  Barclay, Boot and Shoe Maker, with a sketch for self-measurement; H. Monk, Cutler in English on recto and in French on verso; Samuel Neele for Engraving in General; Birks & Pearce, Saddle, Cap and Whip Maker; Thomas Robinson, Ironmonger.
- Virginia Gazette and General Advertiser, 1796 November 9, Original transferred to Newspaper Virginia Richmond. (Box-folder 1:14)
  Newspaper contains two signatures on the upper left corner, W. Nicholas and J. Adams. Includes a pro-Jefferson letter by John Stewart, a candidate for elector, which discusses John Adams' adherence to "monarchical principles" as he finds evidenced in Adams' A Defence of the American Constitutions. Additionally, containing another anti-Adams letter by "A Plebian" responding to Mr. Davis, again providing evidence that Adams is "the most unblushing advocate for monarchy, that has ever appeared in America."
- Thomas Jefferson to Henry Remsen, 1800 March 4, ALS, 1 p.; Photostat of letterpress copy; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:15)
  Mentions envoys at Lisbon, but wants to sell tobacco immediately to Mr. Lieper rather than waiting for the French market. Bordeaux and London tobacco prices, and the problems with leaving the West Indies "out of the operation of the law." Directs Remsen to John Barnes who will pay draft. Congress to adjourn following meetings with envoys who he hopes will "find dispositions to bury the tomahawk as against us, but whether the new government of three in one will be disposed for a general peace, seems yet uncertain."
- Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Thomas Jefferson, 1803 October 30, ALS, 1 p.; Endorsed by T. J.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Mr. Dinsmore left Monticello to go to Philadelphia. Work on canal and well house. Goldsmith's Grecian and Roman histories, Thucydides. Mentions Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr. and John Wayles Eppes.
- Thomas Jefferson to Craven Peyton, 1803 November 27, ALS, 1 p. with envelope; Facsimile. (Box-folder 1:17)
  Concerning either postponing payment on a debt or paying in monthly installments.
- Unidentified fragment, 1804 August 7, AL, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:18)
  Concerning "pleasing melanchol[ic]" remenicences as the author leaves Richmond, their fellow travellers, their driver Gregory, and their arrival at Powell's Tavern in Petersburg, Virginia.
- Thomas Jefferson to [John] Barnes, 1805 April 5, ALS, 1 p.; Photostat; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:19)
  Returning a letter from Mr. Taggert, his interaction with a painter, and the shipment of paint from Philadelphia to Richmond.
- Circular for Biny & Ronaldson, 1809 February 17, D, 1 p. with Photostat. (Box-folder 1:20)
  Requesting information about possible Antimony and Bismuth mines in the United States.
- M[olly] Lewis to Thomas Jefferson, 1812 September 23, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed; Photostat only; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:21)
  Desires that Thomas Jefferson send Jo[seph Fossett?] to help her, and for barrels to be sent to be filled with surplus apples. Mentions reminding Mr. [Hugh] Chisolm of a "small job." Thomas Jefferson's surveying calculations for Shadwell fields on verso.
- Clipping from Richmond Newspaper Regarding the Agricultural Society of Virginia, 18[18] June 26 (Box-folder 1:22)
  Concerning the affairs of the Agricultural Society of Virginia, and a letter about the Hessian Fly's decimation of the wheat crop in Virginia, containing a description and engraving of wheat.
- Map of the World, ante-1820, 1 p.; Torn along old folds into three pieces. (Box-folder 1:23)
- Catalogus Transylvaniensis, 1822, Printed Pamphlet, 29 pp. on 8 l. (Box-folder 1:24)
  This small bound printed pamphlet, written entirely in Latin, contains a short synopsis of each thesis and a list of the "theses, and young men who are initiated in their art." Contains synopses of theses in theology, politics, law, rhetoric, anatomy, physiognomy, mechanics, geology, medicine, astronomy, grammar, mythology, chemistry, archeology, mathematics, logic, natural philosophy, botany, lexicography, history, poetics, agriculture, drama, metaphysics, ethics, and philology. Additionally contains a short history of Transylvania University in Lexington Kentucky, and a list of the "Concilium Curatorum emedaverunt" including Henry Clay.
- Bank Account Statement with Notes in Thomas Jefferson's Hand, 1824-1825, AD, 1 p., Photostat; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:25)
  Sums owed to Farmers Bank, United States Bank, and Virginia Bank.
- Three Jefferson Lottery Tickets, 1826 April, ADS, 3 pp. on 3 l. with Photostats. (Box-folder 1:26)
  Three presumably non-winning tickets for the Jefferson Lottery held in April, 1826.
- Two Locks of Thomas Jefferson's Hair, 1826 July 4, With notes explaining that one was cut but Mr. Trist a few days before Jefferson's death, and the other immediately after Jefferson's death. (Box-folder 1:27)
- Receipt of Thomas Jefferson Randolph to John Taylor Lomax, 1826 August 9, ADS, 1 p.; docketed; with Photostat. (Box-folder 1:28)
  Receipt for five Jefferson lottery tickets.
- Twenty-eight Unsettled Bills to Purchase Articles for Sale at Monticello, 1827, ADS, 29 pp. on 28 l.; Photostat; Originals transferred to Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:29)
- Samuel Smith to Jefferson Randolph, 1830 November 14, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Baltimore, MD on November 14; with Photostat. (Box-folder 1:30)
  Thanking Randolph for a letter of the 7th, and concerning the possible publication of a letter with a suggested ammendation. He additionally mentions that "The Messrs. Bayard" have submitted letters to him that "might be [construed?] to [his] discredit," and desires those letters like the one in question not be given to the public.
- Broadside Poem the Burning of the University of Virginia, 1895 October 27, 1 p.; Original catalogued as Broadside 1895.M377 Copy 3. (Box-folder 1:31)
  A poem by W. G. M., Chicken Peddler, from Union Mills, VA concerning the burning of the Rotunda in 1895, and the hope for a quick rebuilding and recovery process.
- The Daily Progress, 1901 October 12, Original catalogued as Broadside 1901.A8. (Box-folder 1:32)
  Concerning the pilgrimage of the Jefferson Democratic Club of St. Louis to Monticello and their dedication of a monument to Thomas Jefferson. Includes excerpts of speeches by Jefferson Levy, M. E. Benton, and others at the dedication ceremony.
- Newspaper Clipping Regarding Jefferson's Desk, ante-1921, Newspaper clipping, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:33)
  Concerning the immanent return of Thomas Jefferson's desk from the Bismarck Museum in Germany through the efforts of Dr. James F. Dickie.
- Transcript of Jefferson Family Birth and Marriage Records in the Hand of Martha Jefferson Trist Burke, n.d., AMs, 8 pp. on 3 l.; with Photostat. (Box-folder 1:34)
  Compiled by Martha Jefferson Trist Burke from notes by Thomas Jefferson, and the memory of Virginia Randolph Jefferson Trist before her death in 1882. With extended notes taken "from the blank side of a printed page which separates the Psalms from the Prayer book, all the births and earlier deaths in Thomas Jefferson's hand writing," and with a continuation noting in whose hand each subsequent entry was written.
- [Thomas] Jefferson's Engraved Calling Card, n.d., 1 p; with Photostat and photograph copy. (Box-folder 1:35)
- Thomas Jefferson Plat of Harrison Family Land, n.d., AD, 1 p.; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:36)
  Mr. Harrison's mill and Woodson's Ferry. See Nichols, N-558.
- Plat of Nicholas M. Lewis' Land, n.d., AD, 1 p., Photostat; Original in Thomas Jefferson papers. (Box-folder 1:37)
  See Nichols, N-560.
- Letter in French with Separate Notes, n.y. Janvier 9, AL, 3 pp. on 1 l. with Photostat; glued to separate sheet; repaired with "bank note paper." (Box-folder 1:38)
  Including a description of Genes, Italy, and attached to a note claiming that this is an example of a French language exercise written by one of Jefferson's daughters.
- List of Fruit Trees, n.d., AMs, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 1:39)
  Unidentified fragment with incomplete list of fruit trees.
- Newspaper print of Jefferson's Tomb sketched by Theo. R. Davis, n.d., 1 p. (Box-folder 1:40)
- A Visit to Monticello Made by Emma Frances Allen on the 2nd of December 1899, n.d., AMsS, 43 pp. on 43 l. with Photostat (Box-folder 1:41)
  Describing the approach to Monticello, Thomas Jefferson's grave, the history of ownership of Jefferson's grounds, a description of the ruins of the nail factory, and "an ancient black who though nearly blind & quite venerable almost astonished [them] by not claiming to be Jefferson's body servant." Containing an extensive digression on Jefferson's escape from Monticello during British invasion, and the acts of heroism of Martin and Caesar, two of Jefferson's slaves, during the invasion. Including an extensive description of the house and surrounding area, a list of notable visitors, and an anecdote about a meeting between Jefferson and Lafayette on the grounds of his estate. Describes the owner, Jefferson Levy, their barred entry, and providing a hearsay description of Monticello's interior. Writing from Edgehill "the house of a great-grand daughter" of Jefferson, describes Jefferson furniture in Edgehill and the Edgehill manor. Contains an excerpt from a letter by Jefferson to his youngest daughter in March 1791 concerning his interest in birds, the first budding of flora, and asks his youngest daughter to note their first appearances. Describes Jefferson playing games with his grandchildren and his grandchildren's feelings and relationship with him. Contains another excerpt of a letter from Jefferson to his eldest daughter Martha written in 1791, which concerns a calash he had made for her. Contains a physical description of Jefferson, and mentions Gilbert Stuart's portrait of him. Details a brief history of Monticello's ownership following Jefferson's death to the ownership of Jefferson Levy.